The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas by Vanni B. Montana. 6036/014
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas by Vanni B. Montana.
1977-1977
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Montana, Vanni B.
6036/014
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
This collection consists of a typescript copy of Vanni B. Montana's "The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas."
5767194
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 29, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, January 10, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Vanni B. Montana (Giovanni Buscemi) was born February 12, 1902 in Mazara del Vallo in southwestern Sicily. As a socialist in a growing fascist state, Montana fled his native land as a political refugee finding himself first in Vienna, before heading to Berlin and settling in Paris. On his travels, Montana came in contact and befriended other Italian anti-fascists and socialists. During his time in France, he took classes, worked with Italian immigrants, and he helped organize and unionize laborers, diggers, and restaurant workers, arranging strikes and giving speeches. On July 4, 1928, Montana immigrated to the United States and soon found himself surrounded by the Italian-American community and antifascists, becoming employed by the newspapers "Il Lavoratore" and "Il Nuovo Mondo" (later "La Stampa Libera"). He became involved in the Italian socialist movement, organizing rallies against fascism and urging opposition against Mussolini. After the war, Montana was active in the rebuilding of a democratic Italy, and organized one of the first people to people tourism programs to bring Italian immigrants and their American born children to the country.
Montana was a co-founder of the Italian-American Labor Council in 1941, and helped draft the petition to exempt Italian citizens living in the United States from the "enemy aliens" category. For thirty-four years, he was an editor of "Giustizia," the Italian publication of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, as well as the Education Director of ILGWU Local 89 and worked on the "Voice of Local 89" radio program. Montana died in 1991 at the age of 89.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the typed manuscript for Vanni B. Montana's autobiography, "The Shambles: Broken Bridges over the Seas," from 1977. The "Shambles" is the English version of his Italian language autobiography "Amarostico" which is currently available at over a dozen public and academic libraries. Montana interweaves historical events in his hometown of Mazara del Vallo and Sicily with episodes from his youth, illustrating how the political climate and early experiences would influence him later in life. The first section recounts not just life in Sicily, but topics such as socialism, antifascism, communism, and the individuals Montana met as a student and the thoughts and ideas debated among his circle. As fascism grew, Montana found it difficult to remain in his home and country and details his experiences escaping and becoming a political refugee. After immigrating to the U.S., he found himself surrounded by like-minded individuals and aligned himself with the Italian-American community. He discusses his various jobs and organizations he was involved with, including his work with the ILGWU and Local 89, the founding of the Italian-American Labor Council, and his trips to Italy after the war. Montana's manuscript reflects his interest and activities as an Italian-American labor leader and socialist. Researchers may be interested in the organizations discussed including: the Italian Socialist Party (PSI), the Socialist Party of Italian Workers (PSLI), the Italian Socialist Federation of the American Socialist Party, the Mazzini Society, the Italian-American Victory Council, the Italian-American Labor Council, the Office of War Information (OWI), the Amalgamated Clothing Workers Of America (ACWA) and the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU). Notable individuals mentioned in Montana's manuscript include: Carlo Tresca, Sidney Hillman, Luigi Antonini, Generoso Pope, Augusto Bellanca, Giuseppe Modigliani and Ignazio Silone. The Vanni Buscemi Montana Collection located at the George Meany Archives contains correspondence, writings and clippings that Montana amassed to write his autobiography.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/186: ILGWU. Giustizia (Justice) 5780/186 mf: ILGWU. Giustizia (Justice). Microfilm. 5780/023: ILGWU. Local 89. Luigi Antonini correspondence 5780/024: ILGWU. Local 89 records 5780/064: ILGWU. Local 89 minutes
Montana, Vanni B.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5767194
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 1 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Typescript. Pages 1-66.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 2 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Typescript. Pages 67-127.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 3 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Typescript. Pages 128-184.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 4 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Typescript. Pages 185-250.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 5 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Typescript. Pages 251-309.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 6 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Typescript. Pages 310-382.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 7 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Typescript. Pages 383-443.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 8 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Typescript. Pages 444-512.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 9 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Typescript. Pages 513-565.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 10 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Typescript. Pages 566-638.
- The Shambles: Broken Bridges Over the Seas, by Vanni B. Montana [Folder 11 of 11], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Typescript. Pages 639-700.